Welcome to this week's roundup of
everything important that happened in
AI. Coming at you from my grandma's
guest room in Slovakia, Eastern Europe,
visiting family for a few days, but
that's not going to stop me from telling
you all about GBD5 Codeex, which for
many people was reason enough to switch
away from Cloud Code. Interesting. Gamma
3.0, which is an overall of the
application that most people considered
the best tool to create presentations
within up until now. and so many more
stories like agents getting access to
credit cards and more. In this week's
episode of AI news you can use, the show
that takes all of the releases in this
crazy space. We filter by what matters
and then I get to show you live demos of
how these things actually work in
practice and how to use them. Let's
begin. Okay, so let's have a look at
OpenAI's codeex CLI with the new GPT5
codeex model. Yes, the name is getting a
bit more confusing again. I guess now
they're just doing variations of GPT5.
So I have this pre-installed in my
computer. The setup literally took me
less than 2 minutes. I linked it to my
OpenAI account and now I can use the new
GPT5 codeex model within their codec. If
you're still confused by this, this is
their version of clot code. And if
you're not familiar with cloth code, you
might want to check out the 70 80minute
tutorial that I did about a week or two
ago on this channel introducing you to
that, showing what the possibilities
are, showing you how to use it. It's
essentially a command line agent and has
become the go-to tool for agentic
coding. And now with this new model,
it's promising to be even better than
before. And let me tell you, the vibes
all over the internet and the sentiment
towards this are extremely positive. A
lot of people are jumping ship from claw
code to try this out. But then a lot of
it seems to be based on the frustration
they've had over the past few weeks with
clot code as it was delivering
inconsistent results. Now that's sort of
a whole different story, but as we're
talking about it, I might just touch on
that. Enthropic released an article
about the clawed API models being
inconsistent and giving their reasoning
and everything. You can kind of check it
out. But long story short, they're
essentially like, "Hey, okay, we messed
up. Sorry about that." But I think quite
frankly, a lot of the damage has been
done and a lot of people have explored
some of the alternatives. And now
apparently Open I really went for the
kill with this new model release, which
we will test now. So what I'm going to
do is my classic Pomodoro timer test
just to get a feeling for this. I'll
open up a new terminal in folder number
one, claude pomodoro, and open up a
second one with codeex. And then over
here, I'll simply say codeex. Over here
I say claude. Give it permissions.
Proceed. Beautiful. Now we have the new
codeex with the GPT5 codeex model
active. And over here we have claude
where we'll switch the model to opus to
make this fair. Like so. I'll just give
it this prompt. Build a simple pomodoro
timer app with start, pause, and reset
buttons. Show the countdown. 25 minutes
by default. switch to a 5m minute break
after each session and loop the cycle.
Use clean, minimal UI and we'll hit
enter on both of these. And in a sec
we'll have two applications as created
by these two state-of-the-art command
line CLIs which we can judge. And while
it does that I want to forward some
comments that I've heard from some
users. For some people codeex is
unintuitive. They said they way prefer
cloth code and I really wonder why that
is. My experience with Codeex so far has
been very minimal. I'll be very honest
on this. What I did notice is that
usually Codex went ahead and asked a
bunch of questions before starting which
I didn't get right now. It went straight
into just doing. Matter of fact, what I
see here is it's executing on the plan
and while Clot Code asked one time for
an extra permission, Codeex just did it
all. And yeah, right now it seems like
we have the application. So, let's see
what the results are based on what it
told us and then let's review it. Okay,
it outlines the features. Okay, to try
it out, open index.html in your browser.
the timer will keep looping focus break
sessions and then it makes suggestions
for further features. I kind of like
that cloud code as per usual gives you a
list of all the features that it did and
that you can find it in this HTML file.
Let's say open the HTML. I mean heck, if
you're using a command line tool, might
as well take advantage of it. No need to
double click anything. So here's the
version from claude. This is a very
cloud-esque look actually with the
graded background. And then here is the
version from codeex. Let's just have a
quick look. Start. Okay, it's running.
Pause. Reset. Okay, pretty
straightforward. Works as expected.
OpenAI version. Same thing. Works as
expected. Okay, so how about we add a
more complicated feature and see if that
works. I'll just say implement
multi-timer functionality and adjustable
durations. That's nothing crazy, but
that's quite a bit of code right there.
Oh, there goes the claw version.
Finished it first. I was predicted that
I might want to open it. I like that.
So, while Codex finishes, let's give
this a shot. Yeah, let's just do deep
work. 20 minutes. And I add a timer
which I can start. Let's do another one
with 10 minutes. And I add another one.
And now these are running
simultaneously. Yeah, seems like it can
start this one and kind of pause this
one. Aha. And now as I pause the second
one, the 10-minute one stopped.
Interesting. So, that's a bit of a bug
right there. No, it seems like only one
of them can work at a time. I mean, I
guess that could be a feature, not a
bug. Wait, but now none of them is
working. Okay, it got close but not
quite there. Obviously, we could easily
fix that. But let's see if GPT managed
to oneshot this. Okay, so we have the
base timer. We can kind of just start
this. As per usual, Claude was
ambitious. Do you see how it did so much
more with like adding names to it and
that interface where you can like hide
them away? kept it simple, which I
think is an advantage in this scenario.
Can just adjust this to 20 minutes
started and yeah, this actually works.
Look, the simplicity paid off. Ooh, I'm
kind of seeing this now and liking it a
lot. Yeah, this one just works right out
of the gate and it didn't add any
features that I didn't ask for. It's
kind of nice to have all these buttons
and stuff, but yeah, my experience with
CL code is it's incredible, but often
it's a bit over ambitious and you have
to reel it back a little. So, there you
go. In this quick little comparison,
yeah, GPT5 Codeex amazing. And I hope
this quick little test gave you a bit of
a feeling for what these products can
do. And if you still haven't tried them
out, really seriously, go check out that
clot code tutorial. It'll get you
started with essentially both of these.
It is in claw code, but most of the
concepts there work in both of these.
And this is just the most powerful tool
in the AI space to learn these days. So,
I hope this little comparison helped.
Let's see what's next. Next up, we have
something I wish I had a bit more time
with, but I guess we'll just do the same
test we did in the Codeex CLI earlier
on. Well, we just built the simple
Pomodoro app. I just copied that over,
but Replet released agent v3, kind of an
overhaul of their no code building
product. And even if you don't have a
plan, you can kind of just try this
thing out. Log in with your Google
account, give it a prompt, and see what
it comes up with. And there it is. Our
first Pomodoro timer iteration. Let's
just give it a quick spin. Start. That
works. Okay, it added some features
here. Ooh, settings and stuff. I didn't
ask for that. So, this one is ambitious,
too. Not a bad thing, per se. Ah, it's
not even done yet, but it's like kind of
works. Sound notifications, too. Oh,
hold up. This is actually kind of cool.
Look, it looked at the result and said,
I can see there's a Pomodoro timer
implementation, but it's more complex
than what you requested. It kind of read
my mind. But look, hold on. Yeah, it
added statistics, settings, multiple
brake types, and it's fixing itself. So,
yeah, just like before, Replet is more
of a autopilot tool that you can guide
rather than something where you go step
by step, which is really good in many
scenarios. Look, the new version is as
simple as I would expect it to and it's
really easy to host and this interface
just makes a lot of sense. Obviously,
there's many competitors in this space,
and in this channel, we've featured
pretty much almost all the competitors,
but honestly, this is a great option
from what I'm seeing here. And I guess
their agent free product is really
looking to take a bigger bite out of the
market. It just takes a while. I mean,
I've been sitting here for 10 minutes
and it's not even done yet. It seems to
work already, but it just keeps working
and working. Meanwhile, with both Codex
CLI and clawed, I already had the extra
features and I could have took like a 8
minute walk, but hey, speed is not the
priority with these things most of the
time, so that's fine. So, next up, we
have a brand new video model and this
does something we haven't seen before,
which is HDR. It's the Ray Free model by
Lumi. And as it happens, this video is
actually sponsored by Lumaai, which I
absolutely love because we would have
covered this on the show even if they
didn't reach out to us. So, you might
already know Lumi from previous
episodes. This is their dream machine,
which is their AI video generation
platform. And now they have this brand
new rayfree model, which excels in their
visual quality. I would say it has this
very artistic and tasteful style to it.
And it's really good at HDR outputs,
which means high dynamic range. In other
words, that means the difference between
the darkest point and the brightest
point can be absolutely massive while
everything being still visible. So, I
have the product right here and I did
what we always do on this show. We ran
our standard AI video test prompts
through Dream Machine with the new
Rayfree model enabled down here. And
right now, I'm running a second pass of
our test prompts with the resolution
being 720p and HDR enabled. This is
going to give us the ability to really
compare the difference between what a
normal video output would be and these
HDR outputs. And as per usual, we'll
also contrast these with some of the
competition, which is fierce in the AI
video space. Okay, so let's have a look
at some of these standard outputs and
see how they did. Okay, so right off the
bat, you can see that this model uses a
lot of motion. This orbit around the
sloth is quite the movement. I mean, the
camera moves 90° in this case. The water
looks really solid, which is something I
always look for. And the consistency on
the sloth is good, too. If you start
looking really closely for some
artifacts, you can find some in the
leaves, but this is pretty damn good.
And this shot of the sloth in HDR is
just better. Look at all the rich
details in the shadows here. You can see
the entire sky and the highlights in the
water, whereas in the standard version,
when you look into the shadows, it's
just black. That's pretty damn good.
Let's have a look at the next one. Okay,
so the water is actually really good.
And I love the way it did the steam.
This one actually looks better than some
of the competition. Character
consistency is good, too. And overall,
you just have this feel that is quite
artsy. I really want to hop on over to
the HDR look here and see how that went.
So, on this one, it's not visible
immediately. I think we need a shot that
has a bit more contrast. Maybe we'll
look at the ghost shot. So, this is the
SDR shot. And this one is particularly
tricky because of the reflection, right?
It needs to get it right in both spots.
I love the general feel of this one.
While it gets the eyes wrong at certain
points, there's an atmosphere to this
model that I really like. Okay, what
about the HDR version of the ghost? Oh,
this did way better. See how you have
all the rich details in the shadows and
still get the window and the ghost. And
here the consistency between the mirror
and the face is actually super good.
Okay, one last one. What about this man
with the dog? Pretty good character
consistency. I'm actually surprised by
that. And here the background looks
perfect. Comparing to some other models,
the humans on these look super good. And
the HDR version actually does some
lighting changes, which might not be
what you expect, but you can really see
the contrast differences between these
shots and the SDR shots. Yeah, that
delivers. One important note is that you
can even take SDR footage and then
within Dream Machine you can make those
shots HDR enabling a new type of
workflow where you can even take normal
footage and just add the HDR effect.
Interesting. So yeah, that right there
is Ray Free. Go check it out from the
first link in the description below. And
thank you so much to Lumi for sponsoring
this video and making these productions
happen. All right, let's see what's
next. So now we got to talk about a new
image editing model interface. Sure,
it's an image generation model, but I
don't think that's a special part here.
competitors like Nano Banana just
outperformed this on the quality. But
what's really unique here in this
release of Ravez image model and the
interface that comes with it is the
interface part. Now look at that. You
get to generate various parts, various
layers and then combine them. So you
could do something like regenerate just
the handback and then move the hand back
around in the scene. And we went ahead
and tested this to see how well this
works in practice because this seems
like the obvious next evolution of these
applications. you really want is a AI
generation and editing Photoshop like
application, not one where you brush
over something and say, "Hey, change
this." If you want to move the back,
just grab the back and move it to where
it is. I mean, that's the ideal consumer
experience. So, yeah, as I mentioned, we
tested this and we did a few things like
replacing objects. So, you can see we
first generate some lifestyle shots
which look beautiful. I mean, this is a
great image model, don't get me wrong.
But then what we get is not just one
image, but all these layers and these
cutouts. Now, if you want to make this
mug black, you would kind of just edit
those elements right here. And then when
you're done, it's going to regenerate.
And there you go. The mug is black. And
that's really kind of it. It's that
simple. I should say that the same thing
goes for moving objects in the scene and
for changing text in the scene. It has
never been simpler. I really, really
like this interface. I mean, look at
that. If you're doing professional work
with this, if you're designing ads,
posters, whatever, you just grab the
damn product, move it where you want it
to be, or just change the text to what
you prefer. Great interface. In a
similar category, but maybe a bit less
exciting, is the new model Cream 4.0.
It's another image generation and image
editing model similar to Nano Banana. So
what we did is run a bunch of
comparisons to Nana Banana here. And
yeah, here are some of the results.
Adding this bowl of lemons, it's just
different variations of good. No real
opinion on this one. Changing the season
in this shot, I think Cadream was
actually more accurate. And in this one,
where the model was asked to not change
the aspect ratios, Cream changed it
slightly while Nano Banana kept it
consistent. And when we ran our image
benchmarking pros, we just found that
yeah, it's just another good model that
does text. The stars look good.
Honestly, a lot of the new models, they
just look very similar and you can
expect kind of the same things. It's
really this editing ability that is
special. One thing that I will point out
is that when it comes to editing text,
Cream performs even better than Nano
Banana. Look at this one where we want
to change the name from Horizon Labs to
Parallax Labs with a double L and Cream
got it right whereas Nana Banana forgot
a letter. Something to consider. And I
guess in this example, it changed the
suit to a dark green suit, although the
image is black and white. So, the prompt
appearance here is even higher than Nana
Banana. That would be my conclusion.
Great model overall. If you're doing
image editing with AI, try it out. Okay,
now let's have a look at the one that I
personally have been waiting for because
when it comes to presentation creation,
there seems to be consensus amongst all
the people I talk to that the tool to do
it with is this application called
Gamma. They just built the AI PowerPoint
from the ground up and it actually works
really well. This is not affiliated. I
always disclose when that is. It's just
one of those tools that I really enjoy
having at my disposal. And now they
released a brand new release, GMA 3.0,
which overhauls the interface. And I
myself am actually curious to see what
happened here and what I get with the $8
plan I think that I'm paying for. So
apparently there's really two big
changes here. One of them is an agentic
interface where you can talk to it and
form your presentation that way. They
sort of had this before. You could
prompt over the whole presentation but I
guess now it's going to be more
interactive. And they're saying there's
10 times more visual variety which is
amazing. I love that. Yes. Yes, please.
And the second big release, which I'm
not going to be covering here, is that
they have this available through their
API now, which can be really
interesting. Having an API endpoint that
can automatically generate slide decks
for you. I mean, if you're in sales and
do anything related to that, that just
seems extremely powerful. You could take
client calls and they just deliver
custom slide decks after each call. This
is a thing they even pointed out in
their release tweet. But as someone who
does a ton with meeting transcripts of
all sorts, team meetings, client
meetings, etc. This just makes a lot of
sense. Okay, let's get into this and
look at the new interface, Gamma
Frequenc. Zero. What do they have going
on here? Just going to create a new
presentation. Generate it fully. Let's
do it on cats with hats cuz why not? 10
cards. Generate outline. Okay, so this
is still pretty standard. Looks very
similar to what we had before. I guess
the design variety will come in the
presentation editing. Let's see. Cool.
All this content works for me. We're
kind of just testing. Yeah. And then
themes. Okay. So, this is where some of
the new ones come in. Let's see. Okay.
Here on top there's a few new ones. Ooh,
I kind of like this one. Or spectrum.
This looks nice and modern. Uh, actually
I'll settle on Mercury. Okay, good
choices right there. I'll do line art
images and generate the whole thing.
Cats with fats presentation coming right
up. Okay, I love the way it's created.
I'm not sure that this was here before.
I mean, I do use this semi-regularly. It
might have been, but it feels different.
And there we go. Cat Fats, a whimsical
journey from story book to reality. All
right, whatever. We're not going to
judge the content of this. I just want
to have a look at the design, which is
actually really good. I mean, even down
to the images, this did get better. I
can't put my finger exactly on how, but
like all of these are good and they
align with the style. And there's a few
new things. So like there's an agent
here on top. Okay, I'm just going to say
make it more crazy. That's always a fun
one. And every request is free until
October 1st. Okay, it was pretty cool.
Let's see how that goes. Okay, so it
updated the copy to be more crazy. Ooh,
these variations. Okay, so basically
took all the copy and just made it super
crazy. Unleashed a hattacular Feline
Frenzy. Okay, not sure I'm a fan of that
copy change, but hey, that does work and
it's what I asked for. Yeah, I mean
overall this is a clear win. There's new
styles, but the main thing that I
noticed here is that just the design and
the image generation, everything, it
just feels more cohesive. I guess under
the hood, they just started using more
context while generating the images and
they must have updated the pipeline that
creates these presentations because to
me, all these slides, they just feel a
bit more coherent and like experienced
designer made them versus before often
it got you like 60% there, but you had a
lot of work left. Whereas with what I
saw here design-wise, I would say it's
probably 90% of the way there. a very
welcome upgrade. So already a great app
that many people are using. So yeah, if
you have any presentations, I can only
recommend this. Let's see what's next.
And similarly to Gamma 11 Labs, another
one of the big applications in the
space, released a 3.0 version of their
studio application. Again, an amazing
product that is getting even better. So
let's just log in and see what changed
here. So, here are all the generators as
before, but they added this voice
remixing, which is very simply explained
a way to take a voice and create a
variation of it. Not recreating
completely from scratch, not uploading
brand new training data to create a new
voice, just remixing one you already
have. I was actually going to mention
that in the end, it just popped up here.
So, now you know. But that's the studio
release. The studio release is right
here. And the point here is they just
added a bunch of features which you
might have found in other apps into
here. And now you can find all of the
different tools in here, too. So for
example, this AI script generator is
new. It's not something we have never
seen before. It just wasn't available
here. So if I say, write me a short
poem, cats with hats, it will just
generate that for me and then I can keep
working all in one space. And as you can
see, this seems to be a trend right now.
Like all of these different
applications, they're bringing in
features that just make sense and
bundling it into these like studio
experiences where they want you to stay
on their platform from beginning to end.
Okay, let me switch this to the Unreal
Tournament Voice, which is one of my
favorites. Um, if you're not familiar,
that was like a shooter game back in the
day where they just had this legendary
announcer with the most epic voice
imaginable. And I guess if I select
that, I could use tools like the voice
changer or moving background audio right
in here. And then all of these other
functions are in here, too. I could be
adding sound effects. So, how about I
add a cat meow?
That's a good one. And then I can import
it here, and I can place it in the
timeline. Okay, I see. Uh-huh. And then
here, I can add a 1.5 second break.
Maybe shorten the sound effect. And now
it should be that poem read in the
Unreal voice with a meow between these
two lines. Okay, let's see if it worked.
>> A feline friend, a dapper chap
>> with a jy hat upon his nap.
[Music]
That kind of worked. So, see, you can
use this as a editing software, layering
in things like music. And they even
allow you to add video on top here. And
if you add your own audio, they have
these features like caption generation
that you would want in a video creation
tool. So yeah, they just brought
together a lot of the things they had.
Added a few new features and that's it
right there. Kind of cool to bring a lot
of these magical I think that's really
the word AI tools together. I mean, back
in the day when we were playing Unreal
Tournament in school, I would have never
thought that I'll be taking the
announcer's voice, generating cat poems,
and putting AI generated cat sound
effects in between that and then doing
that for a living. I mean, what a job
this is. But hey, I guess this is how we
learn together. All right, let's see
what's next. Okay, next up is something
that excites me personally because it's
really at the core of what we do here
with this channel and with the show and
that's looking at how people actually
use AI. What are the use cases? How do
they put it to work? Two new papers this
week. One from OpenAI, how people use
CHBT and the second one from Enthropic
and their economic index. Particularly
the Enthropic one is really fun to
explore because they did this
interactive interface. You can go by
state. So you could check out, for
example, California over here and what
it breaks down to. Most people use it
for computer and mathematical use cases.
You could also group by category. Number
one thing providing educational tutoring
and academic assistance across multiple
platforms. Nice. Software dev is in
second place. And then you have things
like IT support, edit documents. Yeah,
this is just really great. What about
Florida? What's the number one there?
Software dev assistance. And then the
documents. And then interesting ones
like provide personal relationship
advice and life guidance support. Almost
1.5% of the use case is pretty
significant. I just find this extremely
informative and easy to navigate and
open released something similar with a
bit of a different approach like how
many of the chatdy queries are related
to work. The answer is the later the
user signed up the less they use it for
work. So work was what really drove a
lot of the early adoption and now these
days only about 30% of the usage is for
work and more than twothirds of it are
for personal use. Interesting that and
much more in this document. Go check
them out if this interests you. I know I
found a lot of data points here that
I'll be using for my own educational
work. Whether that's creating courses in
the community or helping companies
succeed with this stuff because with
papers like this, you can base the
education on real world experiences
rather than just feelings. And I love
that. Okay. And for this week segment,
let's start by talking about this
Albanian AI government minister. I mean,
honestly, I don't know what to make of
this. I just wanted to bring this up.
He's supposed to handle public
procurement and they say he's the first
member who's not physically present but
virtually created by artificial
intelligence and the whole reason is
that he's 100% incorruptible. I have so
many questions here like how is he
incorruptible? Can you just like prompt
inject him and then who will be using
him? Who's prompting him? Is he
prompting himself? Who sets that up? I
don't know. I tried to find like all
these details on a story. I couldn't get
them. I guess I'll just keep an eye on
this. But yeah, this is happening.
There's like AI ministers popping up
now. Then we have Google leading with
something they call the agents payment
protocol unifying all these different
companies behind a standardized way for
agents to pay. And I think this is
actually really interesting because it's
kind of an extension of MCPS which are
an open standards to use tooling with
agents. Then I think two weeks ago we
covered the agents.md file introduced by
OpenAI which is a standardized way to
manage context with agents. And now
Google is trying to do the same for
payments essentially making it so that
agents can use your credit card easily
and safely. I mean look obviously that
comes with a lot of problems right but
honestly if you can unite MetaMask
Mastercard all the Gentic apps Visa
American Express and all the other big
companies I mean look at this crap
that's just crazy then this is what
building a new internet that is actually
powered by AI and agents looks like
there's a public GitHub repo now with
all the details on this nothing to do
here really I mean if you want it you
could like download it and try it but I
guess soon we'll have standardized ways
of doing everything with agents which is
kind of great I'm always a big fan of
interoperability and this open approach
Okay. And beyond that, we have this
story out of OpenAI, which seems more of
a legal reaction than anything else. Yet
again, a chativity is going to be
predicting your age based on your
interactions. And then if you're below
18, it's going to introduce parental
restrictions. This is going to be linked
with the parental controls. And I think
in theory, this makes a lot of sense. I
do wonder how this is going to be
implemented though in practice. And the
one thing I personally really care about
is for full-g grown adults to have
access to models that are powerful and
not lobtomized in any way, shape, or
form. I mean, I think some of that is
really necessary for the wider public. I
get that. I just don't want to see this
divide happen where the big corporations
have all of the most capable AI and then
common consumers get the 80% weaker
version of that, which is a scenario
that could easily pan out and parental
control and safety are the perfect veils
to kind of push these sort of
limitations. And that's really
everything for this week's episode of AI
News You Can Use. To round out this
episode, actually, let me pick up the
camera. Let me give you a little bit of
context on where this episode has been
shot from, cuz I think this is pretty
unique. Classic Eastern European
architecture. All right, that's it for
now.